<text>
     <title>THE HISTORY OF HERODOTUS</title>

      <head>BOOK I. THE FIRST BOOK OF THE HISTORIES, CALLED CLIO</heading>

      <paragraph><introduction><sentence>This is the Showing forth of the Inquiry of <name name='Herodotus'>Herodotus</name> of <places place='Halicarnassos' type='city'>Halicarnassos</places>, to
      the end that neither the deeds of men may be forgotten by lapse of time, nor the works
      great and marvellous, which have been produced some by <people people='Hellenes'>Hellenes</people> and some by
      <people people='Barbarians'>Barbarians</people>, may lose their renown; and especially that the causes may be
      remembered for which these waged war with one another.</sentence></introduction></paragraph>

      <paragraph id='1'>1. <sentence>Those of the <people people='Persians'>Persians</people> who have knowledge of history declare that the
      <people people='Phenicians'>Phenicians</people> first began the quarrel. These, they say, came from that which
      is called the <places places='Erythraian Sea' type='sea'>Erythraian Sea</places> to this of ours; and having settled in the
      land where they continue even now to dwell, set themselves forthwith to
      make long voyages by sea.</sentence> <sentence>And conveying merchandise of <places places='Eygpt' type='nation'>Egypt</places> and of
      <places places='Assyria' type='nation'>Assyria</places> they arrived at other places and also at <places place='Argos' type='city'>Argos</places>; now <places places='Argos' type='city'>Argos</places> was at
      that time in all points the first of the States within that land which is
      now called <places places='Hellas' type='nation'>Hellas</places> - the <people people='Phenicians'>Phenicians</people> arrived then at this land of
      <places places='Argos' type='city'>Argos</places>, and began to dispose of their ship's cargo: and on the fifth or
      sixth day after they had arrived, when their goods had been almost all
      sold, there came down to the <places type='sea'>sea</places> a great company of women, and among them
      the daughter of the king; and her name, as the <people people='Hellenes'>Hellenes</people> also agree, was <name name='Io' gender='female'>Io</name>
      the daughter of <name name='Inachos' gender='male'>Inachos</name>.</sentence> <sentence>These standing near to the stern of the ship were
      buying of the wares such as pleased them most, when of a sudden the
      <people people='Phenicians'>Phenicians</people>, passing the word from one to another, made a rush upon them;
      and the greater part of the women escaped by flight, but <name name='Io' gender='female'>Io</name> and certain
      others were carried off.</sentence> <sentence>So they put them on board their ship, and
      forthwith departed, sailing away to <places places='Egypt' type='nation'>Egypt</places>.</sentence></paragraph>
</text>
